Chapter 8. The pulpit.
I had not been seated very long, a man of a certain venerable robustness
entered. Immediately, as the storm pelted door flew back upon admitting
him, a quick, regardful eyeing of him by all of the congregation, sufficiently
attested that this fine old man was the chaplain. Yes, it was the famous Father
Mappel, so called by the whaleman, among whom he was a very great favorite. He
had been a sailor and a harpooner in his youth, but for many years past had
dedicated his life to the ministry. At the time I now write of, Father Mappel
was in the hardy winter of a healthy old age, that sort of old age which seems
merging into a second flowering youth.
For among all the fissures of his wrinkles there shown certain mild gleams
of a newly developing bloom, the spring vger peeping forth even beneath
February's snow. No one, having previously heard his history, could for
the first time behold Father Mappel without the utmost interest, because
there were certain engrafted clerical peculiarities about him imputable to
that adventurous maritime life he had led. When he entered, I observed that he
carried no umbrella, and certainly had not come in his carriage, for his
tarpolin hat ran down with melting sleet, and his great pilot cloth jacket
seemed almost to drag him to the floor with the weight of the water it had
absorbed. However, hat and coat and overshoes were one by one removed, and
hung up in a little space in an adjacent corner, when arrayed in a decent suit,
he quietly approached the pullpit.
Like most old-fashioned pullpits, it was a very lofty one, and since a regular
stairs to such a height would, by its long angle with the floor, seriously
contract the already small area of the chapel, the architect, it seemed, had
acted upon the hint of Father Mappel, and finish the pulpit without a stairs,
substituting a perpendicular side ladder, like those used in mounting a
ship from a boat at sea. The wife of a whailing captain had provided the chapel
with a handsome pair of red worsted man robes for this ladder, which being
itself nicely headed and stained with a mahogany color, the whole contrivance,
considering what manner of chapel it was, seemed by no means in bad taste,
halting for an instant at the foot of the ladder, and with both hands grasping
the ornamental knobs of the manropppes, Father Mappel cast a look upwards, and
then, with a truly sailor-like but still reverential dexterity, hand overhand,
mounted the steps as if ascending the main top of his vessel.
The perpendicular parts of this side ladder, as is usually the case with
swinging ones, were of clothcovered rope. Only the rounds were of wood, so
that at every step there was a joint. At my first glimpse of the pulpit, it had
not escaped me that, however convenient for a ship, these joints, in the present
instance, seemed unnecessary, for I was not prepared to see Father Mappel, after
gaining the height, slowly turn round, and stooping over the pulpit,
deliberately drag up the ladder step by step, till the hole was deposited
within, leaving him impregnable in his little kbeck. I pondered some time
without fully comprehending the reason for this. Father Mappel enjoyed such a
wide reputation for sincerity and sanctity that I could not suspect him of
courting notoriety by any mere tricks of the stage. No, thought I, there must be
some sober reason for this thing.
Furthermore, it must symbolize something unseen.
Can it be then that by that act of physical isolation, he signifies his
spiritual withdrawal for the time from all outward worldly ties and
connections? Yes, for replenished with the meat and wine of the word to the
faithful man of God. This pulpit I see is a self-containing stronghold, a lofty
erandstein with a perennial well of water within the walls. But the side
ladder was not the only strange feature of the place. Borrowed from the
chaplain's former seafarings, between the marble senotitaps on either hand of
the pulpit, the wall which formed its back was adorned with a large painting
representing a gallant ship beating against a terrible storm off a lee coast
of black rocks and snowy breakers. But high above the flying scud and dark
rolling clouds, there floated a little aisle of sunlight from which beamed
forth an angel's face, and this bright face shed a distinct spot of radiance
upon the ship's tossed deck, something like that silver plate now inserted into
the victo's plank where Nelson fell.
"Ah, noble ship," the angel seemed to say, "Beat on, beat on, thou noble ship,
and bear a hearty helm. For lo, the sun is breaking through, the clouds are
rolling off. Serenest azure is at hand.
Nor was the pulpit itself without a trace of the same sea taste that had
achieved the latter in the picture. Its paneled front was in the likeness of a
ship's bluff boughs, and the holy Bible rested on a projecting piece of
scrollwork fashioned after a ship's fiddle-headed beak. What could be more
full of meaning? For the pulpit is ever this earth's foremost part. All the rest
comes in its rear. The pulpit leads the world. From thence it is, the storm of
God's quick wrath is first described, and the bow must bear the earliest
brunt. From thence it is, the god of breezes, fair or foul, is first invoked
for favorable winds. Yes, the world's a ship on its passage out, and not a
voyage complete, and the pulpit is its prow.